Ina E. Gittings collection, 1890-1985
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Ina E. Gittings collection, 1890-1985
MS 283
Gittings, Ina E., 1885-1966
The Ina E. Gittings collection is comprised of two series: Biographical materials, ca. 1890-1968, and University of Arizona, Department of Physical Education for Women, 1923-1985. arrangement varies by series. Biographical materials include photographs, biographical summaries, press releases, newspaper clippings, radio speeches, diplomas, a scrapbook, "50 years of Physical Education, 1902-1952," and other information regarding Gittings' personal and professional interests. Also includes materials written by Gittings and others relating to the Department of Physical Education for Women; as well as a history of physical education legislation in Arizona. Information on the Ina E. Gittings building on the University of Arizona campus is also present.
.8 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Ina E. Gittings was born 14 January 1885 in Wilbur, Nebraska. She attended the University of Nebraska, receiving her A.B. degree in 1906. During World War I, she served as a physiotherapist with the Army Medical Corps, and was afterwards stationed in Tarsus, Turkey, as a relief organizer and worker. In 1920, she joined the University of Arizona faculty as that institution's first director of physical education for women.
She received her M.A. degree from the University of Arizona in 1925, and did additional graduate work at Columbia University from 1929 to 1930. A pioneer in her field, Gittings introduced women undergraduates at the University of Arizona to such sports as archery, horseback riding, swimming, track, and various team sports. After her retirement in 1955, she continued to be active in civic and community activities until her death on 11 March 1966.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Biographical Information, ca. 1890-1968
Series II: University of Arizona Department of Physical Education for Women, 1923-1985
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into two series, Biographical Materials and the University of Arizona Department of Physical Education for Women.
The Biographical Materials include photographs, biographical summaries, diplomas, a scrapbook covering the years 1902 to 1952, press releases, newspaper clippings, radio speeches, and other information regarding her personal and professional interests.
The second series contains articles, clippings, publications, and publicity, written by Ina Gittings and others, relating to the Department of Physical Education for Women at the University of Arizona. Also included is a history of physical education legislation in Arizona written by her, and background information on the Ina E. Gittings Building, the first structure on the University campus to be named after a woman faculty member.
Access Terms
Gittings, Ina E., 1885-1966 -- Archives
University of Arizona -- Dept. of Physical Education for Women -- History
University of Arizona -- Faculty
Physical education teachers -- Arizona -- Archives
Physical education for women -- Arizona -- History
Women college teachers -- Arizona
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Articles
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Material, ca. 1890-1968
  - Photographs. ca. 1890-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General. 1885-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, University of Arizona. 1920-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General. 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General. 1940s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General. 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook. 1901-1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook. 1920-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, Montana homestead. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: University of Arizona Department of Physical Education for Women, 1923-1985
  - Articles. 1926-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Buildings. 1961-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings. 1923-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - History of Physical Education legislation in Arizona. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Physical Education for Women. 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Publication: Fundamentals in Teaching Physical Education. 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Publicity: Past. 1925-1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Publicity: Radio Speeches. 1934-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Arizona. War Services. Women in Allied Fields. 1931-1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)